Finding Aid for Steve T. Koeff Papers, 1928-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Steve T. Koeff Papers
1928-2002
1964-2002
Koeff, Steve T.
03105 Aa 2
Steve T. Koeff was an associate professor of pediatrics and communicable diseases at the University of Michigan Medical School. During his long career as a physician, Koeff was also a member of the neonatal staff at Wayne County General Hospital and a pediatrician at the Plymouth Health Center. His papers reflect his lengthy career at these locations and his dedication to medical student instruction.
4 linear feet
1 16mm film reel
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were received through the Department of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases (donor number 9276 ).
The papers are open for research.
Steve T. Koeff (1928-2002) was born and raised in Flint, Michigan. He received his B.S. and M.D. degrees from the University of Michigan and completed his residency at the University of Michigan, where he was chief resident during 1956-1957. He completed his internship at Chicago Presbyterian Hospital and his fellowship training in neonatology at the University of Michigan.
Koeff was part of the neonatal staff of Wayne County General Hospital, affiliated with the University of Michigan, from 1965 to 1985. During this time, he developed teaching programs for both medical students and hospital staff. When the hospital closed in 1985, his work focused more on the university environment. He later became a pediatrician at the Plymouth Health Center, an affiliate of the University Health System. Koeff was able to supervise interns while also seeing patients at the Plymouth Site.
Dr. Koeff was a caring and compassionate doctor and teacher throughout his career. Above all, he was dedicated to the well-being of his patients and made sure they were treated with dignity. He outwardly objected to staff treating patients as training objects rather than people. Koeff was also concerned about the cost of medical procedures and the social conditions of his patients.
Koeff became unofficial historian of the Department of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases. He kept copies of numerous departmental publications and procedural documents. Koeff was known around the department as the person who knew everything about pediatrics at the University of Michigan.
Dr. Koeff's dedication to pediatrics made him well loved by staff and students. He was awarded the first Department of Pediatrics Teaching Award in 1978. Many students kept in contact with him after leaving the medical school. His joy of teaching comes across in a statement from a 1997 self-assessment (located in Annual Reports/Curriculum Vitae, 1994-1999): "Because of my age I am frequently asked, 'Why don't you retire and do the things you really love to do?' My response is always, 'If I retire, I couldn't not do those things I would most want to do!'" Dr. Koeff taught and practiced medicine until his death in 2002.
Information drawn in part from memorial in June 2002 Regents Proceedings (Page 370).
Steve Koeff's papers were removed from his office at the Medical School shortly after his passing. He collected many departmental and medical center publications. These were transferred to the Department of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases Publications record group retained at the Bentley Historical Library. The remaining papers were divided into five series including: Department of Pediatrics, Pediatrics Curriculum and Counseling, Professional Activities, Teaching Materials and Lectures, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Koeff, Steve T.; Pediatrics--Study and teaching--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Department of Pediatrics, 1963-2004; 1.4 linear feet
  Koeff was unofficial historian of University of Michigan Pediatrics. The Department of Pediatrics (1963-2002, 1.4 linear feet) series reflects his collection of departmental records and bits of history. It contains committee and faculty meeting minutes, annual departmental reports, staff lists, and schedules. This series also documents various Department of Pediatrics awards and events.
  - Annual Reports
    - 1972-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Billing, 1977-1985 (Box 1)
  - C.S. Mott Children's Hospital, Opening, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Chamber Pot Award, 1968-1995 (Box 1)
  - Departmental Website, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Group Practice Board Minutes, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Meetings (no 1993), 1979-2002; 15 folders (Box 1)
  - Failure-to-Thrive Task Force, 1978; 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Future of Pediatric Primary Care, 1994 (Box 1)
  - General Committees, Wayne County General Hospital, 1974-1985 (Box 1)
  - Ralph M. Gibson Obituaries and Remembrances, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Patient Care Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Patient Satisfaction Survey, Pediatric Highlights, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Pediatric Advisory Council, 1973-1979; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Pediatric Continuity Curriculum, 1999-2000; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Pediatric Location Schedule, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Pediatric Primary Care Provider Committee, 1990-1994 (Box 2)
  - Pediatric Senior Staff Meeting, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Pediatrics Secretaries, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Primary Care Advisory Committee, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Review of the Department of Pediatrics, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Robert C. Kelsch Professorship in Pediatric Nephrology, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Round Table Discussion on Provision of Obstetrical Services in the Western Wayne County Area, Greater Detroit Area Hospital Council, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Staff List, 1987-1993 (Box 2)
  - Standards for Pediatric Facilities and Staff Development, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Taubman Medical Library, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Weekly Conference Schedule, 1991
- Pediatrics Curriculum and Counseling, 1968-1998; 1 linear feet
  As an active and concerned faculty member of the Medical School, Dr. Koeff was involved with Pediatrics curriculum development and student counseling. The Pediatrics Curriculum and Counseling (1968-1998, 1.0 linear feet) series contains committee meeting minutes for curriculum revision and pediatric curriculum retreat notes. Pediatric training and orientation manuals, syllabi, and teaching reviews are within this series. Several folders are dedicated to pediatric clerkships, which match medical students with practicing mentors.
  - Ad Hoc Committee for Evaluation of Medical Student Education, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Career Counseling, 1984-1989 (Box 2)
  - Cost of Medical Education Study, 1983-1986 (Box 2)
  - Curriculum and Training, Department of Pediatrics Website, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Curriculum Revision, 1987-1991 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Evaluation Forms, Revision, undated (Box 2)
  - House Officer Orientation Manual
    - 1977 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
  - Medical Student Education Revision, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Meetings with Donita Sullivan, Director of Medical Student Education, Department of Pediatrics, 1987-1989 (Box 2)
  - Memos to Pediatric Faculty Regarding Education, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Neonatal Education, undated (Box 2)
  - Newborn Nursery Handbook, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Obstetrical Nursing Procedures and Policies, 1975-1978; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Pediatric Alumni, undated (Box 2)
  - Pediatric Clerkships
    - Collaborating Hospitals, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Evaluations by Students, 1985-1989 (Box 2)
    - Mentors, 1987-1993 (Box 2)
    - Opportunities, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Requirements, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Theses, 1989-1992 (Box 2)
  - Pediatric Faculty List, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Pediatric Housestaff Education Committee, 1974-1979 (Box 2)
  - Pediatric Nurse Practitioner Program, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Pediatric Retreat
    - 1987, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1989 (Box 2)
  - Pediatric Syllabus (Box 3)
    - 1978 (Box 3)
    - 1987 (Box 3)
  - Pediatric Syllabus Editorial Board, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Pediatric Teaching Evaluation Study, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Perinatal Nursing Protocols, 1985; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Perinatal Students, 1970-1974 (Box 3)
  - Policies and Procedures for Students, Wayne County General Hospital Newborn Nursery, circa 1968 (Box 3)
  - Revision of Medical School Bulletin, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Rounding Rooms, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Student Advisory Committee, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Subcommittee for Grand Rounds, House Staff Education Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Undergraduate Medical Education, circa 1995 (Box 3)
  - William Beaumont Hospital (Royal Oak, MI) Medical Education, 1986
- Professional Activities, 1928-1999; 1 linear feet
  Professional Activities (1928-1999, 1.0 linear feet) contains papers documenting Koeff's business affairs. Included are notes and minutes from several professional organizations. The Annual Reports/Curriculum Vitae are especially rich indications of Koeff's personal and professional activities. He added to these files almost every year of his career. The Important Documents and Personal File include such items as his birth certificate, Pediatric Exam Results, and licenses to practice medicine. This series also contains personal and professional correspondence and some of his publications.
  - Annual Reports/Curriculum Vitae, 1961-1999; 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Clippings (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1975; 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Important Documents, 1928-1984 (Box 3)
  - Metropolitan Detroit Pediatric Society, 1969-1986 (Box 3)
  - Neonatal and Hospital Care Committee, American Academy of Pediatrics, Michigan Chapter, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
  - Neonatal Society, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Pediatric Education Forum, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Perinatal Association of Michigan, 1974-1986 (Box 4)
  - Personal File, 1955-1986 (Box 4)
  - Promotions, 1963-1977 (Box 4)
  - Publications, 1961-1975
- Teaching Materials and Lectures, 1960-1993; 0.4 linear feet
  The Teaching Materials and Lectures (1960-1993, 0.4 linear feet) series contains notes and presentations from some of his classes. Introduction to Clinical Skills 510/511: Physical Examination contains particularly rich information about the "Visit a Doctor's Examining Room" Program. Koeff would invite local preschool children to visit a doctor's office and play with instruments and interact with medical students. It was his way of introducing both the children to a comfortable medical environment and getting medical students acquainted with children. The folders contain many cards from the participating children. The series also contains text and notes from many of his lectures to colleges and professional societies.
  - Introduction to Clinical Skills (ICS) 510/511 Introduction to Clinical Skills/Physical Examination
    - 1990 (Box 4)
    - 1991 (Box 4)
    - 1992 (Box 4)
  - Introduction to Clinical Skills (ICS) 600/601 Physical Examination Techniques, 1986-1989 (Box 4)
  - Emergencies in the Newborn Lecture, April 15, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Idiopathic Respiratory Distress Syndrome: Where We Stand Today, undated (Box 4)
  - Infections in the Newborn Infant Lecture, January 24, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Inteflex (IFX) 400 Ethics and Human Values in Science, Medicine, and Society, 1986; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Junior Seminar Schedule, Wayne County General Hospital, 1971-1984 (Box 4)
  - Lecture Materials and Forms, undated (Box 4)
  - Management of Respiratory Distress Syndrome for Faculty Practice Review, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Objections to Introduction to Clinical Skills Executive Committee, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Post Graduate Conferences, 1960-1974 (Box 4)
  - Resident Evaluations of Teaching, 1971-1981 (Box 4)
  - School Age Child Lecture, April 22, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Teaching Schedule, 1986-1992
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials (1962-1994, 0.2 linear feet) series contains photographs and one film. The photographs mainly contain pediatrics staff group images and house officers portraits. The 16mm film depicts the resuscitation of a newborn child.
  - Photographs
    - House Officers, 1966-1994 (Box 4)
    - Junior Pediatrics, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Pediatric Staff, 1967-1985 (Box 4)
    - Science Writers Meeting, 1962 (Box 4)
    - James Wilson, Portrait, undated (Box 4)
  - 16mm Film: Resuscitation of the Newborn, circa 1964 (Box 4)